Guide to the ILGWU Records, 1884-2006, bulk 1923-1995.
ILGWU Records, 1884-2006, bulk 1923-1995.
- SERIES IV. EXECUTIVE OFFICERS AND STAFF, 1911-2006
  - Subseries B. Other Officers and Staff, 1911-2006
    - 5780/199 P. Murray Gross photographs, [1949-1981.], This collection contains photo albums, as well as photographs of Murray Gross with Richard Nixon, Robert F. Kennedy, Lyndon B. Johnson, John F. Kennedy, Adlai Stevenson, and others.
    - 5780/206. Alan Howard papers, [1970-1997.], Country files include correspondence and notes, printed material, and newspaper clippings on countries in which the ILGWU had a special interest, especially the Dominican Republic and Honduras. Company files include correspondence, memoranda, notes, and press material on companies with which the ILGWU dealt; especially well-documented is the strike against and negotiations with Leslie Fay. Subject files include correspondence with and collected printed material on labor leaders and politicians, as well as on subjects relating to the garment industry and trade.
    - 5780/126. James Lipsig papers, 1946-1970., Contains correspondence, testimony, and other material relating to James Lipsig’s work as Assistant Executive Secretary of the ILGWU. Also included are minutes of the Finance Committee and the Education Committee.
    - 5780/082. James Lipsig papers, 1948-1978., Contains the records of James Lipsig, Assistant Executive Secretary of the ILGWU, as well as Treasurer of the ILGWU Campaign Committee from 1966 to 1976. Included are files on the Campaign Committee, Congressional redistricting, disability, displaced persons, equal employment opportunity, the Jewish Labor Committee, and Unity House. Meeting minutes include those of the Campaign Committee, Education Committee, Union Health Center Committee, and the Socialist Party USA’s New York State Convention. Reports include those from local unions summarizing their responses on their Local Union Equal Opportunity Report to the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission. Also included are correspondence and applications relating to the ILGWU’s Displaced Persons Project whereby the union sought admission of 400 individuals per the Displaced Persons Act of 1948. Lipsig’s records also contain a draft manuscript of Gus Tyler’s Organized Crime in America: A Book of Readings (University of Michigan, 1962).
    - 5780/130. Local 153 records, 1954-1955., This collection consists primarily of transcripts of arbitration proceedings between Local 153 of the Office Employees International Union and the ILGWU, and related statements and exhibits.
    - 5780/154. President's office records, 1981-1985., Consists of files maintained by Jay Mazur during his tenure as Secretary-Treasurer of the ILGWU. Included are correspondence and memoranda with staff at the ILGWU's departments, as well as regional departments, joint councils, and local unions. Records also include agreements and documentation relating to various investments and funds.
    - 5780/152. David Melman papers, 1974-1992., Contains the files of Executive Assistant to the President David Melman from 1974 to 1992. Included are extensive company files which include correspondence and other materials relating to contract negotiations. Also included are records on General Executive Board meetings and ILGWU conventions, as well as general subject files.
    - 5780/143. James Parrott papers, 1980-1991., Correspondence, reprints, and congressional testimony of James Parrott, Executive Assistant to the President, International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Parrott’s records consist primarily of subject files, many of which pertain to ILGWU organizing around proposed changes on the regulation of homework, as well as around the New York City's apparel industry, especially the Garment Industry Development Corporation.
    - 5780/150. Carl Proper papers, 1975-1994., The papers of Carl Proper consist primarily of subject files and files on labor-management committees.
    - 5780/187. Irwin Solomon papers, 1965-1998, Contains the files of Irwin Solomon during his tenure as Executive Vice President and later General Secretary-Treasurer of the ILGWU. The collection consists primarily of correspondence files, but also includes financial reports and files pertaining to the merger of the ILGWU and Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers of America to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial, and Textile Employees (UNITE).
    - 5780/069. Leon Stein collection, 1911-1977., Contains draft manuscripts of Leon Stein’s writings, drafts of his translation of the work of Abraham Cahan, research material for books on the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire in New York City and the Ludlow (Colorado) massacre, and some correspondence.
    - 5780/087. Leon Stein records., Leon Stein’s papers include draft manuscripts of Stein’s own writings, several of Stein’s unpublished manuscripts, drafts of Stein’s translation of the work of Abrahan Cahan, research material for Stein’s books on the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire in New York City and the Ludlow (Colorado) massacre, correspondence, and assorted clippings and printed material.
    - 5780/087 mf. Triangle fire trial transcript and summary. Microfilm, 1911., This collection contains a summary and partial transcript of the Triangle Fire trial, People of the State of New York vs. Isaac Harris and Max Blank, as well as issues of New York Journal and New York Evening Journal from March and April 1911.
    - 5780/087 P. Leon Stein photographs, This collection consists of photographs transferred from the Leon Stein papers. Photocopies of the photographs were inserted in the original locations to identify transferred documents.
    - 5780/003. Louis Stulberg correspondence, 1956-1966., The Stulberg General Secretary-Treasurer records consist primarily of correspondence dealing with union managerial matters during Stulberg's term in office, though there is also some correspondence from his tenure as executive vice-president (April 1956-May 1959), as well as a small amount (ca. 1 linear foot) of personal correspondence in the collection. Among the most signficant topics are: civil rights (including materials on the 1963 March on Washington); collective bargaining agreements with other unions (custodial and clerical workers' unions); health care (including Medstore plan for prescription drug discounts to union health members); housing for garment workers in New York City; locals, regional departments, and joint boards of the ILGWU throughout the U.S., Canada, and Puerto Rico; relations with the AFL-CIO; retirement funds; union administrative matters; union conventions; union involvement in politics in New York City and New York State; and workers' compensation.
    - 5780/052. Gus Tyler papers, 1952-1980., Chiefly correspondence and articles with and by Gus Tyler from the 1950s to the 1970s. Series I consists of Tyler's correspondence. Series II is made up of subject files, dealing with both union and non-union matters. Series III contains both correspondence with and articles by Tyler. Individuals represented include: Abraham Beame; Sol Chaikin; Wilbur Daniels; David Dubinsky; Arthur J. Goldberg; Andrew M. Greeley; Averell Harriman; Hubert Humphrey; Jay Lovestone; George McGovern; John F. Kennedy; Robert F. Kennedy; Charles Silberman; Leon Stein; Philip Taft; and Abraham Weiss.
    - 5780/096. Gus Tyler papers, 1959-1996 [bulk 1975-1995]., Correspondence, subject files, articles, transcripts of broadcasts, photographs, and other materials dating from the end of the 1950s to 1996. Series I consists of both ILGWU and non-union correspondence. Series II is made up of subject files, dealing with both union and non-union matters. Series III contains publications, writings, transcripts of radio and television broadcasts, and other materials. Series IV consists of miscellaneous materials, including photographs, cassette tapes, and ILGWU publications.
    - 5780/088. Gus Tyler papers, 1958-1981., Contains Gus Tyler’s records, documenting his work as Political Director of the ILGWU, writer, editor, and lecturer. In addition to general subject files, records include administrative files, documentation of political activity and speaking engagements, and Tyler’s writings, including columns and work for his book Organized Crime in America.
    - 5780/005. Frederick F. Umhey correspondence, 1934-1955., The Umhey Executive Secretary records consist primarily of organizational records, subject files, and correspondence dealing with union administrative matters. Much of the collection is made up of routine correspondence. There is, however, significant material documenting such ILGWU activities as the annual convention, Union Health Center, Unity House (the ILGWU resort), and Unity Broadcasting Corporation, which owned a number of radio stations across the country. In addition, the collection contains correspondence with government officials about labor situations in the garment industry during World War II, and information about health care, benefits, and pensions for workers. Some of Umhey's personal records are also included.
- SERIES V. GENERAL EXECUTIVE BOARD, 1900-1995
  - 5780/016. General Executive Board minutes, 1913-1995., Includes the minutes and reports of the General Executive Board of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
  - 5780/016 mf. General Executive Board minutes, 1913-1995., Includes the minutes and reports of the General Executive Board of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
  - 5780/018. General Executive Board. Appeal Committee Cases, 1926-1956., Contains correspondence and case files of the Grievance Committee, Appeal Committee, Special Investigation Committee, and Election and Objection Committee of the General Executive Board.
  - 5780/189. Perry Parker papers, 1986-1989., Contains the papers of Perry Parker, consisting primarily of minutes and reports of the General Executive Board meetings between 1986 and 1989, as well as some of Parker’s notes.
- SERIES VI. CONTRACTS AND CASE FILES, 1907-2000
  - 5780/075. Collective Bargaining Agreements, 1907-2000., Consists of agreements and contracts between the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and associations of garment manufacturers.
  - 5780/075 mf. Collective Bargaining Agreements. Microfilm., Consists of agreements and contracts between the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and associations of garment manufacturers.
  - 5780/145. Association Agreements, Out of business contracts, 1914-1994., This collection consists of agreements and contracts between the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and defunct associations of garment manufacturers.
  - 5780/191. Association contracts, [1916-1994.], This collection consists of 800 agreements and contracts between the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and associations of garment manufacturers.
  - 5780/146. Master Agreements, Out of business contracts, 1941-1994., This collection consists of agreements and contracts between the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and defunct garment manufacturing firms.
  - 5780/147. Independents, Out of business contracts, 1943-1995., This collection consists of agreements and contracts between the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and defunct independent garment manufacturers.
  - 5780/158. Out of business contracts, 1988-1998., This collection consists of contracts between the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and defunct garment manufacturing firms.
- SERIES VII. DEPARTMENTS AND INSTITUTIONS, 1884-1999
  - 5780/114. Apparel, Job Training, and Research Corporation records, [1974-1981.], Contains application files from shops and workers therein to participate in the Apparel Job Training and Research Corporation’s training program, financial records, and reports. Application files include applications from shops for certification with AFTRC, agreements between the AJTRC and shops for on-the-job-training, applications from individuals for enrollment in the AJTRC, and related correspondence. Financial records include invoices and related correspondence. Reports address conditions in the apparel industry.
  - 5780/111. Archives Department records, 1900-1987., Contains correspondence, forms, and other files pertaining to the archives’ everyday operation, as well as photocopies of materials from the ILGWU records on a variety of topics and local unions, and collected printed material about the ILGWU.
  - 5780/121. Archives Department. Robert Lazar papers, 1890-1985, In addition to documentation of the archives’ everyday operation, the papers of ILGWU archivist Robert Lazar include photocopies of materials from the ILGWU records, collected printed material about the ILGWU, sheet music, meeting minutes of local unions, and accounting ledgers.
  - 5780/121 PUBS. Archives Department collected publications, 1895-1987, Contains publications collected by the Archives Department.
  - 5780/192 PUBS. Auditing Department publications, [1935-1994.], Contains publications of the Auditing Department, including statements of receipts and disbursements (1935-1960), census reports (1952-1984), and financial reports of general funds (1961-1994).
  - 5780/214. ILGWU Chorus records and sheet music, [1989-2000.], This collection primarily consists of sheet music of the ILGWU Chorus. Also included are a few records relating to the chorus.
  - 5780/214 P. ILGWU Chorus photographs, Consists of photographs relating to the ILGWU Chorus, including portraits of chorus director Malcolm Dodds.
  - 5780/177. Communications Department biography files., Biographical files on union members, union officers, and political and public figures.
  - 5780/177 P. Communications Department photographs., This collection consists of photographs transferred from the Communications Department’s biographical files on union members, union officers, and political and public figures.
  - 5780/176. Communications Department records, 1987-1995., Consists of alphabetical subject files maintained by the Communications Department.
  - 5780/176 P. Communications Department photographs, 1909-1995., This collection contains photographs used by the Communications Department of the ILGWU. Included are photographs documenting ILGWU events and organizations, including conventions and other meetings, strikes and rallies, and local unions and regional departments. Also included are photographs of ILGWU presidents and other officers, political figures, and prominent labor unionists.
  - 5780/104. David Dubinsky Foundation records, 1949-1978., Records include correspondence with reports from organizations that had received grants, meeting agendas and minutes of the foundation’s Board of Trustees, and summaries of successful applications. Also contains a manuscript that chronicles the work of the David Dubinsky Foundation.
  - 5780/106. Education Department. Beverly Schulman papers, 1972-1991., Consists of materials on several of the ILGWU’s training institutes, seminars, and conferences.
  - 5780/138. Education Department. Kitty Krupat papers, 1990-1995., Krupat’s papers include correspondence, memoranda, reports, and financial records relating to the ILGWU’s independent and collaborative education projects, including the Worker-Family Education Program, the Joint Union-University Committee on Labor Education, and the Consortium for Worker Education, as well as numerous trainings, conferences, and seminars. Also included in the files are materials from local unions and regional departments of the ILGWU, files on the Internationals’ conventions, and reports to the General Executive Board.
  - 5780/166. Education Department records, 1920-1979., Contains correspondence, memoranda, and reports documenting the work of the Education Department between 1920 and 1979, including material relating to several of the ILGWU Education Department’s Social and Education Centers in New York City such as attendance sheets and correspondence of Fannia Cohn.
  - 5780/166 PUBS. Education Department publications, 1920-1995., This collection consists of publications either created or collected by the Education Department. Publications include speeches and articles by Fannia Cohn and Mark Starr, and reports of the Education Department and the Ladies Apparel Accessories Council.
  - 5780/086. Educational Department. Jasper Peyton papers, 1963-1982., Series I contains subject files including correspondence, memoranda, news releases, pamphlets and notices, and routine paperwork. Also included in this series is correspondence materials directly related to Jasper Peyton’s duties as Assistant Education Director; most of these materials are from 1971 and 1972. Some odd photos are dispersed through the collection. Series II includes Educational Reports to the General Executive Board, Educational Activities Reports, correspondence, questionnaires, and routine paperwork. Series III includes several issues of Publishers’ Weekly and assorted anti-Communist printed material.
  - 5780/049. Educational Department. Fannia M. Cohn papers, 1918-1962., Correspondence, subject files, speeches, articles, photographs, and programs from Fannia Cohn's term as Executive Secretary of the ILGWU Education Department. The materials in Series I are primarily letters between Cohn and various individuals pertaining to trade union matters in general and the ILGWU in particular. Included in the series are programs for lectures, concerts, museum visits and tours of New York City that were offered to ILGWU members and others as part of the Education Department's activities. This collection is also available on micorfilm.
  - 5780/049 P. Educational Department. Fannia M. Cohn photographs, 1920-1960., Collection consists of photographs pulled from the Fannia Cohn papers. Photographs include portraits of Cohn, as well as document activities of Local 66, trips to Unity House, Triangle Factory fire commemoration, and other union activities.
  - 5780/208. Health and Safety Department records, [1953-1995.], Arranged alphabetically by name, the company files document the Health and Safety Department’s participation in the investigation and improvement of conditions in workplaces around the country, including correspondence, memoranda, and reports on shops. The Health and Safety Department also maintains several subseries of subject files: one was on workplace hazards; these are arranged alphabetically by industry. A second was a general subject file that included topics relating to the routine business and research of the department; these are arranged alphabetically by topic. The third is constituted of the health and safety organizations of other unions, as well as unions outside of the United States. The final series contains training materials, including files pertaining to specific trainings, files of handouts on specific workplace hazards, and files of graphics and originals used in the production of the department’s training materials and publications.
  - 5780/062. International Relations Department records, 1968-1995., The International Relations Department records consist chiefly of the correspondence of its director, Henoch Mendlesund, during his tenure from 1968-1980, and Michele Briones. The collection also includes articles, reports, conference materials, photographs, and other items. The materials in this collection have an emphasis on labor issues in the developing world. There is correspondence with leaders of clothing and textile workers' unions in India, Japan, Turkey, Kenya, Latin America, Namibia, South Korea, among other countries. Other items concern conventions and conferences of the ILGWU that emphasized international issues, visits from foreign union leaders to the ILGWU, and visits of ILGWU leaders to foreign countries. There are also some materials about garment workers' unions in Western Europe. Topics addressed include working conditions, human rights, economic, political, and social conditions in developing countries, and requests for aid to assist foreign unions.
  - 5780/062 PUBS. International Relations Department publications, 1919-2000., Consists of publications either created or collected by the International Relations Department of the ILGWU.
  - 5780/107. Legal Department records, 1958-1980., Contains files relating to the ILGWU’s organizing and legal activities surrounding the Kellwood Company at several of its divisions throughout the southern United States (Little Rock, Arkansas; Lonoke, Arkansas; Brownsville, Kentucky; and Greenfield, Tennessee). In addition to court documents and correspondence and memoranda relating to the ILGWU’s legal cases, these records contain documentation of the Kellwood strike, including surveys of strikers, organizing leaflets and newsletters (from both the union and the company), and newspaper clippings on the strike. Also includes Steve Honeyman’s draft accounts of the strike, transcripts of his interviews with ILGWU members and staff who participated in the strike, as well as working materials from the negotiations between the ILGWU and Kellwood. Organizing leaflets from other shops in Arkansas, Missouri, Nebraska, and Texas are also included.
  - 5780/107 AV. Legal Department audio-visual materials, 1976., Contains audio recordings of interviews with ILGWU members relating to working at and, later, striking against the Kellwood Company, as well as notes relating to these interviews. Also included are several tapes on sweatshops, some of which feature Frederick Siems.
  - 5780/107 P. Legal Department photographs, [1967-1972.], This collection consists of photographs taken during the ILGWU strike against the Kellwood Company between 1967 and 1972. Included are images of meetings and rallies, as well as of the memorial service Eugene Hampton. Hampton was an ILGWU member who was killed during the strike.
  - 5780/081. Legal Department records, 1928-1982., Consists of case files, case summaries, incomplete case files, contract histories, subject files and miscellaneous materials from the Legal Department between 1928 and 1982.
  - 5780/063. Legal Department records, This collection contains correspondence, memoranda, financial reports, and printed material relating to the establishment of the ILGWU’s cooperative housing in New York City, as well as research into similar projects elsewhere. Also included in this collection are files on the Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Center in New York City, arbitration regarding faulty design and construction of Unity House in the Pocono Mountains, Pennsylvania, and contract negotiations in 1979.
  - 5780/162. Donnelly Garment Company v. ILGWU. Legal documents, 1935, 1937, 1939, 1942., Contains transcripts, briefs, and other legal documents relating to Donnelly Garment Company v. ILGWU.
  - 5780/085. Legal Department. National War Labor Board case files, 1936-1946., This file includes arbitration notes, correspondence, Cotton Garment Industry Application for Wage Adjustments, legal documents, N.W.L.B. - Application for approval of wage or salary rate adjustment or schedule, notes, and payroll summaries covering the period 1936-1946.
  - 57805780/140. Library listing of selected material., This collection consists of photocopied catalog cards of materials transferred from the ILGWU library to the Kheel Center.
  - 5780/118. Management Engineering records, 1941-1980., Contains the Management Engineering Department’s research material and reports on technological changes in the garment industry, as well as correspondence, reports, and other material relating to the department’s investigation of conditions in specific shops.